<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Psalmes of confession found in the cabinet of the most excellent King of Portingal, Don Antonio, first of that name, written with his owne hand. Wherein the sinner calleth vpon the mercie of God for his sinne. Translated out of the Latine copie, printed at Paris by Federike Morell.</title>
            <title>Psalmi confessionales. English</title>
            <author>António, Prior of Crato, 1531-1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108316</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843977</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 166:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Psalmes of confession found in the cabinet of the most excellent King of Portingal, Don Antonio, first of that name, written with his owne hand. Wherein the sinner calleth vpon the mercie of God for his sinne. Translated out of the Latine copie, printed at Paris by Federike Morell.</title>
                  <title>Psalmi confessionales. English</title>
                  <author>António, Prior of Crato, 1531-1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Bishop, R. Nuberie, and R. Barker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Psalmes of confessions for sinners.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C¹² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Marsh's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:8753:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:1"/>
            <p>PSALMES <hi>OF CONFESSION,</hi> found in the Cabinet of the moſt excellent King of Portingal, <hi>Don Antonio, first of that name, written with his owne hand.</hi> Wherein the Sinner calleth vpon the mercie of God for his ſinne. <hi>Tranſlated out of the Latine copie, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Paris by Federike Morell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by G. Biſhop, R. <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, and R. Barker.</hi> Anno Domini. 1596.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Psalms">
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:2"/>
            <head>PSALMES OF CONFESSION, wherein the Sinner cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon the mercie of God for his ſinne.</head>
            <div n="1" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſhal giue water vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Eſai. 9.</note> my head, and a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares for mine eyes, that I may be able to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and bewayle the loſſes of my ſoule with griefe agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto? for there is a manifeſt and great cauſe of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, when with the ſight of my minde I behold mine aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient dayes, and my youthfull yeeres: in this meditation my<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> ſpirite hath failed me: for I<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.</note> knowe what I was, yea rather what I ſhould haue beene, and vnderſtand what I am, and
<pb facs="tcp:8753:3"/> feare what I ſhall be: and the leſſe I ſorowe, ſo much the more I feare. I would to God I ſorowed more, that I might feare leſſe. But woe to me, O Lorde, for nowe a long time thou ſmiteſt, and yet I ſorowe not: thou calleſt, and yet I heare not: thou knockeſt, and yet I open not the barre of my heart. The ſorowes of death<note place="margin">Pſal. 114.</note> compaſſe me rounde about: and being filled with many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes without, I feele inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no ſorowe that may worke vnto ſaluation. And I feele not onely the ſorowes of old age, but I am a man of ſorow from my youth vpward, and all my<note place="margin">Pſal. 87.</note> dayes are full of trauaile and griefes: and yet I ſorowe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that alway ſorowing, I<note place="margin">Pſal. 53.</note> cannot ſorowe. O marueilous<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.</note> and vnſpeakeable wiſedome of the heauenly Phyſitian! O
<pb facs="tcp:8753:3"/> wonderfull goodneſſe of the high King! O ſingular bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of him that is the giuer of all good things! for thou, O God, giueſt vnto me ſorowe, leaſt I periſh in pleaſures, and that I may learne to reioyce without offence: thou giueſt me ſorowe for a time, that I may not ſuffer euerlaſting paines: thou afflicteſt my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that thou mayeſt ſaue my ſoule: thou ſcourgeſt, that thou mayeſt heale: and killeſt, that thou mayeſt quicken. But alas, vnwillingly doe I receiue thy ſalue out of the ſecrete hand of thy mercie: and being ignorant, doe not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoueraigne medicine of healthfull ſorowes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou art mercifully ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere againſt me, and how doe I acknowledge it. If I earneſtly deſire to be deliuered from ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:4"/> who without ſorowes cannot be healed? for howe ſhall he be healed without ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, who by delightes is made ſicke? Therfore, O Lord, make me to ſorowe, and teach me a ſauing ſorowe, that my griefe may be turned into ioy,<note place="margin">Iohn 16. Pſal. 12.</note> and that I may reioyce in thy ſaluation, ſaying: <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt. As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. II.</head>
               <p>DAyes paſſe, and yeeres ſlide away: but I vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie man, who after ſo many corruptions of my ſoule, after ſo many moſt grieuous and long falles, doe not yet repent, nor am afflicted for my ſinnes, neglect the often falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into them, care not for riſing from them, heaping
<pb facs="tcp:8753:4"/> newe vnto olde, and greater vnto leſſe. What ſhall I doe, O Lord? or whither ſhall I goe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 138</note> when my laſt time ſhall come? where ſhall I be hidden from the countenance of thy wrath? or whither ſhall I flie away from thy face, when thou ſhalt call me vnto iudgement, and require of me accompt of the talent giuen vnto me? What ſhall I anſwere vnto thee? or howe ſhall I excuſe my negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, when thou ſhalt ſit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the throne of thy Maieſtie, and command me to giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of my ſtewardſhip to<note place="margin">Matth. 5. Luke 16.</note> the vttermoſt farthing? Surely I will ſay, Lord, I ſuffer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, anſwere for me: for who<note place="margin">Eſai 38.</note> am I that I ſhoulde anſwere vnto thee in iudgement? But what if thou compel me to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere? I will ſay as a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, fearing, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling:
<pb facs="tcp:8753:5"/> O Lord, I haue gained<note place="margin">Matt. 25.</note> nothing thereupon. Yea I haue<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> wickedly and vainely conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thy talent, and by looſe liuing I haue ſpent thy goods. ſurely I haue ſpoken fooliſhly, by ſaying liuing: for I ſhould better haue ſayed by dying. But I then thought I liued, and loe I was dead, becauſe I liued without thee my true life. And if I liued at any time with thee, I ſcarce remember it. Yea, if the life of a wicked man, may rather be called death, then life, I may worthily ſay, that I ſooner began to die, then liue. For I did not perfectly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what life was, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had forſaken thee that art the life of liues, and the fountaine of life, &amp; malice did ſupplie mine age in manifold wickedneſſe. I was ſcarce come out of my mothers wombe, and already
<pb facs="tcp:8753:5"/> was a ſinner. Comming into the world, being yet ignorant of ſinne, I did bewaile the ſinne wherein my parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte me: neither did I altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaue bewailing others ſinnes, when I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted mine owne which I knowe, and did not be wayle. Being an infant, I followed iniquities, and ſpent my childehood, wherein I<note place="margin">S. Auguſt.</note> ſhould haue beene pure, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purely: there breathed ſinfull vapours from the ſlimie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of my fleſh, and the ſpring of my youth, and did ſhadow my heart, that it could not diſcerne light from darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the cleerenes of the mind, from the miſt of luſt: and traitrous and craftie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures did carie my weake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull looſe age, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long rockes of luſt, ſo as I boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp in whorings, deſiring
<pb facs="tcp:8753:6"/> to be ſatisfied in hell: from my childehood I grewe to grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yeeres, neither was I ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner growing towards youth, then my wickednes did growe ripe: and I was bold to growe wilde in diuers and ſhadowie luſtes, by the which being drawen and entiſed with the gulfe of wickedneſſe, I was<note place="margin">Iames 1. 1. Tim. 6.</note> drowned to death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The euill and wicked dayes of my growing yeeres paſſed on, and I grewe toward youth: but I returned back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſo much filthie in vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as I was elder. I was a yong man, and came to be a man: but vice alwayes flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in me in ſteade of vertue. I waxed olde and gray, and did not walke in thy wayes: but as a child of an hundred yeres, being nowe an olde man, I liue childiſhly. Where then
<pb facs="tcp:8753:6"/> haue I beene at any time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent that I would be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of thee according vnto the time of mine innocencie, though thou diddeſt appoint it me vnto iudgement? For<note place="margin">Pſal. 118. Pſal. 61. Iob. 9.</note> thou art iuſt, O Lord, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is thy iudgement, and thou rendereſt to euery man according to his workes. And I feare all mine, becauſe they are the workes of darkeneſſe: and I haue beene a worker of iniquitie from the beginning, and haue alway willingly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the pathes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous. I haue wallowed in ſinne as the ſwine in filthines, and as he was fed with coddes: ſo was I delighted with filthie and vaine wordes, and grieued with earneſt &amp; profitable ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I did communicate with thoſe that wrought iniquitie, &amp; did banquet with the chiefe
<pb facs="tcp:8753:7"/> of them, &amp; did glorie in ſinne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> being mightie in iniquitie. I loued to excuſe, and could not accuſe my ſelfe, and made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie my heart: and the more vncurable is my ſinne, for that I did not thinke my ſelfe to be a ſinner. Neither did I only not ſeeke a medicine for my ſoule, that was ſicke vnto death, but refuſed it being offered: yea, with an vnreuerent and vnta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med mind was wroth againſt them, that would miniſter it vnto me. I perſecuted them that reprooued me, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced them that ſpake plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly to me, and was deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their ſpeeches, that had not their heart right vnto thee. I ſtudied deuiſes and lies, and in all things loued rather dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> then light. Beholde, O Lord, I haue declared my ſelfe vnto thee: this is the courſe of
<pb facs="tcp:8753:7"/> my life, wherein I haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thy wrath. This will I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto thee, when thou ſhalt aske me of me: But doe<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> not remember the offences of my youth, nor my ignorances, O Lorde: and enter not into<note place="margin">Pſal. 142</note> iudgement with thy ſeruant, for no liuing creature ſhall be iuſtified in thy ſight: but if thou<note place="margin">Eſai. 61.</note> wilt enter, becauſe thou art a God that loueſt iudgement, doe iudgement vnto me, but not iuſtice, and iudge me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> to the iudgement of thoſe that loue thy name, that I may ſing vnto thee mercie<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.</note> and iudgement. Remember, O Lord, that though I am wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yet am I thy ſeruant, and the ſonne of thy handmaide,<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.</note> and doe not looke vnto the multitude of my miſeries, but vnto the greatnes of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies:<note place="margin">Abak. 3.</note> and when thou ſhalt be
<pb facs="tcp:8753:8"/> angrie againſt me for my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: remember thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that thou bee not angrie with me for euer, but haue mercie vpon thy afflicted ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that my ſoule may praiſe thee, and confeſſe thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghost. As it was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. III.</head>
               <p>VVOe vnto me, O wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man, becauſe I haue made my Redeemer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie againſt me, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliouſly neglected his Law. I haue willingly forſaken the right way, and as a ſheepe that<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.</note> refuſeth his ſhepheard, I haue beene caried farre and wide round about through drie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watered places, wandring in the wilderneſſe, and not in the
<pb facs="tcp:8753:8"/> way. I haue gone to all rough vnacceſſable places, and euery<note place="margin">Sapi. 3.</note> where was anguiſh and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. I haue beene wearied in the way of iniquitie and perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and haue walked in hard wayes, ſeeking reſt, &amp; finding none, becauſe I did not ſeeke thee, O Lord, but was in a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren lande, in the countrie of death, where is no reſt, but continuall labour and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſpirit dwelleth there. When I was in honour, I did<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.</note> not vnderſtand: but as one of the flocke of brute beaſtes, my dwelling was among the walkes of wilde beaſts. I dwelt in anguiſh with pleaſures, and among thornes did I make my bed, and ſlept in death, and hoped for reſt in torments. Nowe therefore what ſhall I doe? whither ſhall I turne my ſelfe in theſe ſo great dangers?
<pb facs="tcp:8753:9"/> All the hopes of my youth are fallen downe, and I am made like one that hath ſuffred ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, who hauing loſt his merchandize, ſwimmeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way naked, being toſſed with wind and ſea. I am caried farre from the hauen, and doe not take hold of the way of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but am caried away on the left hand. The enemie hath placed nets for me which way ſoeuer I went, and ſnares for my feete: and I deſpiſed them, and walked ſecurely in ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie places, and flattered my ſelfe in ſinnes. I thought youth was not helde by the lawe of death, and being deceiued by this confidence, I followed the filthie deſires of my fleſh, and gaue the raines beyonde all meaſure to ſenſualitie, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it whither ſoeuer the force thereof did carie me: and ſaid,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:9"/> a foole in my heart, wherfore<note place="margin">Pſal. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> doeſt thou thinke of the ende before the middle? thou haſt many dayes yet remaining, and maieſt be conuerted when thou liſteſt. So waxed I olde in ſinnes, and a moſt wicked cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was turned into nature: and nowe like a bondſlaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Barnard.</note> ſinne, I ſerue as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chained, and as a mad man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his owne fleſh, ſeeketh to hurt himſelfe, all reaſon of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation being quenched: ſo I more grieuouſly and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly haue hated mine owne ſoule: for the impenitence of my heart, and obſtinate wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, hath layed violente and wicked hands vpon me, and hath torne in pieces and exulcerated my ſoule: and ſo hauing brought vnto my ſelfe the heapes of hell, euery day more and more according to
<pb facs="tcp:8753:10"/> my hardneſſe and impenitent<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> heart, I doe whoord wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of wrath. I haue made triall ſometime to ſhake off the olde yoke, but am not able, becauſe it cleaueth to my bones. O that at length it may fall from my necke, that I may loue thee though late, it ſhall ſurely ſal away, if thou O Lord command, and ſend me helpe from aboue. I confeſſe I haue not deſerued it, but thou, O moſt gracious giuer, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt the Sunne to riſe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently vpon the good and bad, and graunteſt temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to the vnworthy, euen when they aske them not: how canſt thou denie ſpiritual things to thoſe that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them? Haue mercy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpon me, O Lord, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the deſire of a poore man, thou that art riche in mercie,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8753:10"/> and art woont cheerefully to<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> haue mercie, and doeſt purge the will from euill cuſtome, and heareſt the gronings of<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> thoſe that are bound, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt vs from the bands which we haue made vnto our ſelues, vnleſſe we raiſe vp againſt thee the hornes of falſe libertie. Giue thy right hand vnto the<note place="margin">Iob 14. Pſal. 36.</note> worke of thine owne hands, that when I fall, I may not be bruiſed, and being bruiſed, I may not be drawen into the<note place="margin">Eſai. 14.</note> deepe lake, wherein is no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouth<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> of the cruell lyon, that is ready for the praye, and gapeth after my ſoule, that he may deuoure it: for thou onely art my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour and deliuerer, and in thy mercie alone is all my hope. Let thy mercie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Pſal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> be done vnto me, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as I haue truſted in thee.
<pb facs="tcp:8753:11"/> I haue truſted, and ſhall not be confounded, but obtaining my deſire, ſhall ſing vnto thee: <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt. As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. IIII.</head>
               <p>MY nightes paſſe away in grieſe, and vexe me with innumerable terrors: my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhaketh me while I am awake, and I am tormented therewith as if I were woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a two edged ſword: my ſleepe is troubled with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers illuſions, bringing me no reſt but trauaile: I watch all night in my thoughts, &amp; when as being wearied I endeuour to giue ſome ſleepe to mine eye lids, by and by ſleepe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from mine eyes, and I ſleepe alwayes in ſorowes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wakened with an vnquiet
<pb facs="tcp:8753:11"/> wearines from the care of the<note place="margin">Iob 30.</note> day, and all my inward partes are inflamed without reſt. The<note place="margin">Iob 33.</note> meate which before I deſired, is made abominable vnto my ſoule, and my drinke is ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> with teares, and confuſion is before mine eies, and rednes in my cheekes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how grieuouſly I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thee, O my God, and in howe many ſortes I haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed my ſtrength and thy gitfes: I haue ſpent my dayes in vanities, euerlaſting cares haue conſumed me, and being caried hither and thither with ſenſeles cogitations, I haue ſpent my time. I fained to my ſelfe dreames oftentimes, and reioyced: and vaniſhed away being deluded in my vanities and madnes: I aſcended into<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.</note> heauen, and by and by deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto the deepe: and while<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8753:12"/> one deepe calleth another, my ſoule did conſume in euill, &amp; I did rot before the eies of men. I wiſhed impoſſible things, &amp; by the fantaſticall fruition of them, I was made like vnto them that ſleepe, and riſing from their ſleepe, haue found nothing in their hands. I am a vile worme, and yet, O Lord, I did neuer know thee, but with an high forehead haue exalted my ſelfe alone aboue all. I haue raſhly boaſted of my wordes, and in pride thought them to be wiſedome. I was an enemie vnto my companions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angrie with many did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche them without cauſe. I hated patience &amp; loued wrath, and would be angry without reaſon. I curſed my ſeruants and familiars, yea and my ſelfe alſo when I was angrie, and ſcornefully reproched my
<pb facs="tcp:8753:12"/> friends. I did vnwillingly beare mine aduerſities, and haue put my truſt in man, more then in God. I heard the trueth vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, and anſwered the wiſe in furie. I ſought iniuries and reuenges willingly, and neuer reſerued reuenge vnto God. I waxed cruell againſt him that defended his owne cauſe: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did a ſoft anſwere, or a<note place="margin">Prou. 6.</note> gentle man pleaſe me. I tooke pleaſure in ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as a wicked man, did often ſow diſcord &amp; hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I receiued with mine eares wholeſome and good counſels, but did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend diſcipline. I did with a milde countenance beholde ſuch counſailours as tickled mine eares: but thoſe that ſpake vnto mee with a free minde, I put farre from me. I<note place="margin">Tobia.</note> helde not out my hand to the
<pb facs="tcp:8753:13"/> needie, neither did I eate my<note place="margin">Tobit.</note> bread with the hungrie: the beggers and lepers did lie in the ſtreetes, and I paſſed away turning mine eies from them, leaſt my bowels ſhould be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and I moued with mercie, ſhould giue almes vnto them. I payed not my debt to them that did lende vnto me, and did borowe to ſatisfie my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate deſire. I coueted to be rich, that I might doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull things, and in all godly dueties ſhewed my ſelf poore: and what I wanted to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, did largely abound vnto my luſt. I reioyced beyonde meaſure in all gluttonie and bankets, and with vnſatiable greedineſſe, offended nature that is contented with little. My belly was as it were my<note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> god, &amp; my glory in the ſhames of thoſe that ſauour earthly
<pb facs="tcp:8753:13"/> things. I ſought the ſweeteſt and moſt exquiſite meates: and with the pretence of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie I did often ſhadowe the deſire of pleaſure. I put my<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> portion among the adulterers, and my familiar conuerſation was among fornicators. I was immoderately conuerſant in blood: and being like vnto bruite beaſtes, I was ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in this vice, that I ſhame to ſpeake, what I ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not to doe. Mine eare and my tongue ſerued vanitie, whileſt by the one, the oile of ſinners did make my head fat, and with the other I ſupplied often that, which others ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to want concerning my prayſe: and as oportunitie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I did ſet foorth to others mine owne prayſe, and did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reioyce to be ſet foorth both by mine owne, and other
<pb facs="tcp:8753:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8753:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8753:15"/> mens ſpeeches. To conclude, I liued in all kinde of pleaſure of this world, being baniſhed farre and wide from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes of thy houſe: and if at any time the feare of death, and the laſt iudgement did quicken my ſlouth, and for a litle time call me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deepe gulfe of pleaſure, by and by I returned as a dogge to his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite. Being dead in them, I yet liue, and abiding in death, I haſten to death, and ſee death alſo ſwift by comming vnto me. But let thy mercy, O Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> quickly preuent me, before that terrible day of miſerie and calamitie doe come, the great<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> and bitter day, that though I<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.</note> die, I may liue, and declare thy mercies aboue all thy workes, Looke backe, O Lord, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde howe my ſoule lieth in her concupiſcences ſicke of
<pb facs="tcp:8753:15"/> the palſie, and is euill vexed there with: deliuer it from the faſt birdlime of death, that it may cleaue vnto thee alone, who onely art the true life, and leauing all others follow thee that art aboue all. Say vnto my ſoule, O Lord God of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27. 54. Math. 15</note> be it vnto thee as thou deſireſt: make me to heare this thy voyce, a voyce of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and ſaluation, that I may runne after it, and take hold of thee, and keepe thee faſt, and not let thee goe, vntill thou ſendeſt me whole away. For being ſicke, to whom ſhall I goe but to thee, that I may be cured: or who can heale mine infirmitie, but he that for man &amp; mankind came downe from heauen, that they might be healed of their griefs? who can<note place="margin">1. Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> quicken, but he that doth mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie &amp; quicken all things? who
<pb facs="tcp:8753:16"/> can ſaue but thou, O my God my Sauiour, in the time of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation? ſaue therefore and quicken me, thou that art the life and euerlaſting ſaluation of al that put their truſt in thee. And to thee that art without<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> beginning, be glorie without end: to thee be praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to thee be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, thankeſgiuing, thou that art the euerlaſting ſpring of mercies: for I was gone farre from thee, and did runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and yet thou doeſt ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily come to him that is ſicke and runne away, when he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon thee, &amp; doeſt graunt him health, before thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt his ſighes: for to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be healed is ynough, that thou ſhouldeſt heale, and to be willing to liue, that thou ſhouldeſt graunt life, and in the bleſſing of thy ſweetenes
<pb facs="tcp:8753:16"/> doeſt thou preuent the deſire<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> of a ſinner that doeth knowe himſelfe. Therefore I will ſay vnto thee, O Lord, and it ſhall ſuffice vnto me, I knowe mine<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> iniquitie, &amp; what is it to know? but I will bee healed? and howe doe I know? becauſe all my bones are vexed within me, and my ſoule is very much<note place="margin">Pſal. 60.</note> troubled for my ſinnes. Behold nowe, I lay all mine iniquities before thy ſight, O my God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> that thou mayeſt cure &amp; heale my ſoule, becauſe it hath ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thee. For as thou<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> art a God, that deſireſt not ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: ſo wilt thou not the death of a ſinner, but rather<note place="margin">Ezec. 18.</note> that hee ſhould be conuerted, and liue. For the dead ſhall not prayſe thee, O Lord, but wee<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.</note> that liue, doe bleſſe the Lord, and confeſſe vnto him: for he is good, and his mercie is
<pb facs="tcp:8753:17"/> euerlaſting. <hi>Glory be to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghost. As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. V.</head>
               <p>I Haue reuealed my miſeries vnto thee, O Lord, not to make knowen my wayes vnto thee, that diddeſt know them all from the beginning, and haſt numbred all my ſteps: for<note place="margin">Iob 31.</note> thou knoweſt the hidden pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of darkneſſe, and all things<note place="margin">Pſal. 43.</note> are naked and open to thine eyes, and thou doeſt not onely ſee, but alſo diſcerne the lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.</note> places of our thoughtes, and the marrowe of our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: but I vncouer that thou maieſtcouer, and protect, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale that thou mayeſt hide, and knowe in me an humble and contrite ſpirite, and by the<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> offring of this ſacrifice, which
<pb facs="tcp:8753:17"/> is moſt acceptable vnto thee: be mercifull vnto me, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue<note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> my ſinnes: I haue ſpoken many and great things, and yet haue ſaide little: for the worme of my conſcience doth<note place="margin">Barnard.</note> pricke me in more, I would to God it might gnaw away the rottenneſſe, that by gnawing it might conſume it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all be it ſelfe conſumed: and that it begin not to be cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in immortalitie, but let it bite, that it may die, and by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little by biting leaue biting. But woe vnto me, for when I thinke I haue made an ende of telling my euils, then am I conſtrained to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as it were, and my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie being full of vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doeth more abundantly remember much more filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for I haue ſinned aboue the number of the ſands of the
<pb facs="tcp:8753:18"/> ſea: and if I had a hundred tongues, &amp; a hundred mouths, I ſhall skarſe anſwere one of a thouſand thouſand: yet that increaſeth my griefe, that I can not remember all my filthines paſt, and the fleſhly corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my ſoule: for while I commit newe ſinnes, I forget the olde, but thoſe that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I will not hide, not that I wil loue them any more, but that I may loue thee moſt earneſtly, O my God: and that I remembring my moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wayes in the bitterneſſe of my remembrance, thou mayeſt<note place="margin">S. Augu.</note> be ſweete vnto me, O ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that art not deceaueable, O amiable ſweetenes, O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and ſecure ſweetenes, then enuie was familiar vnto me, and charitie was eſtranged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, I ſlandered Kings &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Miniſters of the
<pb facs="tcp:8753:18"/> Church, and did bite them with a lying murmuring, I did diſgrace the deſertes and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the iuſt, and allowed the doings of the wicked: if at any time there were a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note place="margin">Fra. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch.</note> ſpeeche concerning good men, I obiected falſe ſpots, and did diſcouer their ſecret infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, &amp; for moſt light things did accuſe them to others, as guiltie of a greater crime. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if there were any infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the wicked, I did by and by ſet forwarde their ſlender vertues, and preferred them in deſert before their betters, and ſo was cauſe of their greater ruine. If I ſawe a thiefe, I did<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.</note> runne with him, and to fulfill mine iniquitie, I rayſed offence againſt my mothers ſonne, &amp; ſpared not to ſlander and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my kinſefolke. I wiſhed to my neighbours ſorrow and
<pb facs="tcp:8753:19"/> ill happe, and in his death one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did I ſet my hope. I did not defend the cauſe of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, &amp; did vpbraide the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as if I reioyced at their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I raſhly iudged many guiltie of faultes, and ſeeing a litle moate in my brothers eie, I did not feele a great beame<note place="margin">Luke 6.</note> in my owneeie: I loued ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe as my mother, &amp; idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was as my brother, and I did auoide all honeſt exerciſe and labour: I waxed heauie from day to day, and did not giue God thankes for his day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly benefites beſtowed vpon me: and thou, O Lord knoweſt howe ſeldome I did by night meditate vpon thy lawe, and thy wonderfull workes: I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſpent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole night with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſleepe, and when my mind did wander from thee hither and thither to many things,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:19"/> thou diddeſt neuer meet with it. I went to bed without thee, I lay in my bed without thee, I roſe from my bed without thee, without thee the day ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon me, &amp; paſſed wholly away without thee, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was I alway without thee, becauſe I was alway with my ſelfe, who in my darke affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons am farre from thee: yet if at any time thou cameſt into my minde, and that I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to conſider thy marueilous workes, ſuddenly the burthen of the worlde (as in ſleepe is vſuall) did ſweetely preſſe me downe, and my thoughtes wherewith I did meditate on thee, were like the endeuours of thoſe that would wake, and yet conquered with the depth of ſleepineſſe, are drowned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. I often purpoſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of the affaires of my
<pb facs="tcp:8753:20"/> conſcience, but the preſent day doeth alway delude me with the expectation of that which is to come. I reſted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a brittle and deceitfull foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and leaned vpon a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken reede, &amp; when as truſting thereto, I thought I ſtood ſure, I fell into the fire, and when I<note place="margin">S. Augu.</note> fell, I knewe howe weakely I had ſtood. I gaped with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencheable thirſt after ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and gaine, and in theſe deſires I ſuffered moſt cruell difficulties. Euery diſordered &amp; vndiſciplined man was my friend, and I defiled the veine of friendſhip with the filth of concupiſcence, and obſcured the whiteneſſe thereof with helliſh luſt. Tragicall ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles full of the ſhowes of my miſeries, and the foode of my fire did drawe me: and I did not only not ſhut the paſſages
<pb facs="tcp:8753:20"/> againſt death, but opened al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<note place="margin">S. Barnar.</note> the windowes vnto it, and all my members were ſeuerall windowes through the which death entred into my ſoule. And ſo newe filthineſſe grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, I haue not purged the olde: nay rather from thence did ſpring in me many ſinnes, for which I am caſt out from before thy face, O my God, &amp; being depriued of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thy preſence, I fall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt into deſperation, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not whither I goe: but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from thee, whither ſhall I goe? and who wil looke vpon my face, if thou turne thine away from me? and as a reprobate depriue me of thy ſight? I ſhall vndoubtedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hatefull vnto all men, and as a wanderer and runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate in the land, I ſhalbe made a ſhame &amp; skorne vnto them,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:21"/> when they ſhall aske of me, where is thy God? and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> hath he put thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him? what ſhall I doe therefore, O wretched man that I am, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſee my ſelfe eſtranged from thy protection, and forſaken in the middeſt of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that fight mightely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me? I wil ſeeke thy face, O Lorde, and with ſighes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thy countenance not to leaue me, nor in anger to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thy ſeruant: for all mine enemies followe me as a fugitiue, that they may take &amp; kill me, and therefore I muſt ſeeke refuge at thy hands, to whom I doe flie, O my God, my ſtrength, my refuge, and my vertue, in the day of my tribulation: for as there is no<note place="margin">Eſai. 45.</note> God beſide thee, ſo alſo there is no Sauiour beſides thee. Thou therefore, O Lord, that
<pb facs="tcp:8753:21"/> knoweſt all my miſeries, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 102</note> from whom the worke of my weakeneſſe is not hidden: caſt behind thy backe all mine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and doe not remember my old iniquities, but ſaue me<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> according to thy mercie, from all thoſe that perſecute me, and deliuer me, becauſe there is none that can redeeme nor ſaue, but thou, O Lord, who ſaueſt all that truſt in thee, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 71.</note> deliuereſt the poore from the mightie, and from the handes of them that are ſtronger then he: hide not therefore thy face from me, O Lord, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me, my ſauing God, my ſtrength, and my deliuerer: for<note place="margin">Pſal. 85. Pſal. 10.</note> I am poore and very needie, and thine eyes looke vpon the poore, and if thy iuſtice ſeeke me, hide me in the boſome of thy mercie, wherein thou haſt with long ſuffering borne me,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:22"/> and inuited me to repentance: for thou art long ſuffering, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> and very mercifull, and excellent aboue al wickednes:<note place="margin">Ioel 2.</note> yea nothing is more proper vnto thee, then to ſpare and haue mercie alwayes: and therefore thou haſt mercie on all, becauſe thou canſt doe all, and diſſembleſt the ſinnes of men for repentance, and thou<note place="margin">Sapi. 11.</note> ſpareſt all, becauſe they are thine, O Lorde, who loueſt ſoules. Turne therefore vnto me, who am turned vnto thee, &amp; deliuer mine afflicted ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all danger, that my mouth may be filled with thy prayſe, and ſay vnto thee: Bleſſed be<note place="margin">Pſal. 123.</note> the Lord who hath not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me to be deliuered vnto the teeth of mine aduerſaries: Except the Lorde had beene my helper, they had perhaps ſwallowed mee quicke: my
<pb facs="tcp:8753:22"/> ſoule as a ſparrowe was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the ſnare of the fowlers, the ſnare is broken, and I am deliuered. <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt. As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. VI.</head>
               <p>O Wretched man that I am, what ſhall I doe? for the great wilde beaſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured my ſoule, and I haue bene made a praye to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, he hath ſpoiled me of all thoſe goods wherewith thou, O Lord, hadſt beautified me, and I am afraide to appeare naked before thee: I departed rich and beautifull from thy<note place="margin">Eſai. 37. Ierem. 11 Oſee. 5.</note> face, and went wandring after filthineſſe in a corrupt way, and in the wickedneſſe of my heart: and my ſoule is made blacke vpon the coales, and
<pb facs="tcp:8753:23"/> the excellent colour thereof is<note place="margin">Thren. 4.</note> changed, and I that was nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with ſpices, haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced dung, and I haue ſo impoueriſhed and deformed my ſelfe by wearing the vile garments of ſinners, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the likeneſſe of Adams offence, as thou, O Lord doeſt not nowe knowe me, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the image wherein thou haſt created me: and wilt not ſuffer mee as a ſcabbed ſheepe, to dwell among the ſheepe of thy paſture. Howe then ſhal I preſume to returne vnto the preſence of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Maieſtie, (in whoſe ſight<note place="margin">Iob 15.</note> the Heauens are not cleane) being emptie, vile and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane? or howe ſhall I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to communicate with thy choſen people, being made fooliſh by offending. I would hauereturned vnto thee
<pb facs="tcp:8753:23"/> though aſhamed and afraide, truſting to thy mercie: for thou art a ſweete father to thy ſonne that is trauailing into a farre countrey; but much ſweeter vnto him when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth from a long pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: But, O my God, I lacke the power to come vnto thee: for I am kept faſt bound by a moſt cruell robber, not with ſtrong iron, but with the iron of mine owne will, whereof the enemie hath made a chaine for me, and bringeth my heart in hard workes and all wicked<note place="margin">Exod. 1.</note> ſlauerie to bitterneſſe. My re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge<note place="margin">Pſal. 118</note> is farre from me: for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is farre from ſinners, and I am compelled to die in moſt miſerable bondage, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou, O Lord, looking downe from Heauen, doeſt helpe me: I ſticke faſt in the ſlimie claie of the deepe, and a
<pb facs="tcp:8753:24"/> tempeſt of temptations, euen like the waves of the cruel ſea, hath ouer whelmed and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me ſo that I am in deſpaire of auoiding theſe imminent dangers, vnleſſe thou, O God, ſhalt take me vp: for the more I endeuour to ariſe, the more am I bruiſed: I am both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without troubleſome vnto my ſelfe, &amp; euery where I finde domeſticall enemies, that doe beate me downe: I looke on the right hand and the left, and I ſee none to whom I may ſafely commit my ſelfe: but euery where feare doeth ſhake me, and to whom ſo euer I come, I finde not a faithfull friend, &amp; how ſhould I finde any, that my ſelfe doe not keepe my faith giuen to my God? I haue ſought any to comfort me in my afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and calamities, and there
<pb facs="tcp:8753:24"/> was none of all my deare<note place="margin">Thren. 1.</note> friendes that woulde comfort me: but I met with men that were too full of wordes, nay dumbe rather, and therefore dumbe, becauſe thy word, O my God, did not ſound from their lips, but the offence of<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.</note> their mouth, the wordes of their owne lips, who did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne my wantes without compaſsion, and triumphing ouer me, did hardly and fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouoke ſtrife againſt me. I haue often conſented vnto<note place="margin">Prou. 18.</note> fooliſh deceiuers, and ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from the right pathe, I ignorantly agreed to their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and by little and little was by them brought to ſuch toyes and madnes, as (though by the helpe of thy grace, I neuer departed from the true religion) yet I did beleeue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fables: yet am I an vnexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable
<pb facs="tcp:8753:25"/> man, for that (when I did knowe thee to be alwayes a God in trueth, I did not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> thee in ſpirit and trueth:) but changed thy trueth into lyes, and ſerued the creatures rather then the Creatour, and ſought my ſelfe and my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in corruptible things: but thou, O Lord, my ſweeteneſſe, and my truſt, proceede on, and as thou haſt made me by true faith to acknowledge thee, waken mee vp that ſleepe in<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> ſinne, and open mine eyes, that I neuer ſleepe vnto death: Lighten, kindle &amp; lift them vp<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.</note> vnto thee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thy light they may behold thee, the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting light, the vnquencheable light, that neuer faileth, the<note place="margin">Eccle. 24.</note> ſweete and delightfull light, that they may ſee and reioyce<note place="margin">Sapi. 4.</note> and couet thy light, and know<note place="margin">Eccle. 11. Pſal. 68.</note> that nothing is to be loued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb facs="tcp:8753:25"/> thee, but in and for thee.<note place="margin">Iohn 1.</note> Thou, O Lord, which art the true light, that doeſt illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate all men comming into this world: cauſe this light to riſe in my darkenes, and make me to deſire thy iuſtification, that my ſoule being melted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the force of loue, may faint into thy ſauing health,<note place="margin">Pſal. 188.</note> and thirſte after thy delightes: my ſoule, I ſay, but let me call it thine, becauſe thou diddeſt make it, and giue it vnto me, and mine, becauſe I receiued it from thee: keepe therefore thy creature, which thou haſt ſpecially framed according to thine owne image, and ſuffer not thy precious gifte to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, wherein thou haſt lifted me vp aboue all the workes of thine owne hands: vpon my body and members, worke whatſoeuer pleaſeth thee, let
<pb facs="tcp:8753:26"/> my fleſh be clothed with rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe,<note place="margin">Iob 33.</note> and conſumed with wormes: But I beſeech thee, O Lord, onely ſpare my ſoule, and ſtretch not out thy hand againſt it, bring me backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into thy wayes, before the going downe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne: for it groweth towarde Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and compell me to come vnto thee, if to call be too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, conſtraine me as it pleaſeth thee: ſo I may come and not periſh, not for my ſelfe, who hauing ſo often abuſed thy mercie, haue made my ſelfe vnworthy thereof: but for thy holy Name, take from me a ſtonie heart, and giue vnto<note place="margin">Exec. 36.</note> me a fleſhy heart, and place thy Spirite in the middeſt of me, that I may walke in thy precepts, &amp; keepe thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I come too late vnto thee, O Lorde, I confeſſe, I
<pb facs="tcp:8753:26"/> would to God I had come ſooner: but I knowe and am aſſured, that thou preſcribeſt no time to them that come, ſo they come, and receiueſt the laſt as gently as the firſt: for that although thou hateſt<note place="margin">Sapi. 1.</note> ſinne, thou hateſt not the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, neither doeſt thou reioyce in his deſtruction: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though hee tarrie very long, thou doeſt patiently looke for him: O how ſweete and pleaſant is that thy ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, O Lord? wherein thou haſt giuen hope vnto my<note place="margin">Pſal. 118. Hiere. 3.</note> ſoule? Thou haſt played the harlot with many louers, yet returne thou vnto me, &amp; I wil receiue thee. How delightfull and pleaſant is that worde, wherewith thou comforteſt ſinners that are in deſpaire of themſelues? If a ſinner repent<note place="margin">Ezec. 18.</note> him from all his ſinnes, he
<pb facs="tcp:8753:27"/> ſhall liue and not die: for is the death of a ſinner accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my will? With great ioy I heare thee when thou ſayeſt, that the ſheepe that<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> had gone aſtray, ſhall be brought home with ioy vpon the ſhepheards ſhoulders, and<note place="margin">S. Augu.</note> that the groate ſhall be layed vp in thy treaſures, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours reioycing with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that found it: and the ioy of the ſolemnitie of that houſe doeth force teares from me, when I did reade of the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſonne, that he was dead, and liued againe. Therefore<note place="margin">Pſal. 67.</note> giue, O Lord, vnto my ſoule, the voyce of thy vertue, and not of thy vertue alone, which ſhaketh off the ſlouthe of ſoules, but alſo the beame of thy light, which doeth both ſhewe vnto men their ſinnes, and giueth light alſo to the
<pb facs="tcp:8753:27"/> hidden places of darkeneſſe.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> Let thy voyce ſounde in the eares of mine heart, and ſay vnto my ſleeping ſoule, why art thou ſo long oppreſſed with a deadly ſleepe, and kept captiue in bandes? It is nowe<note place="margin">Rom. 13. Eſai 55. Cant. 6.</note> time to riſe from ſleepe, and that thou forſake thy waye, and returne to me that haue redeemed thee: returne, O<note place="margin">Eſai. 44.</note> thou Sunamite, returne that we may behold thee: returne, and deferre no longer to come vnto me, for I am the Lorde thy God that call thee, I am, I am he, that blot out thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities<note place="margin">Eſai. 43.</note> for my ſelfe, neither carie in remembrance things paſt: then will I ſay boldly to my ſoule, turne thee to thy<note place="margin">Pſal. 144</note> reſt, for the Lorde hath done well vnto thee: goe ſafely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and though thou art wearied by thy wicked wayes,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:28"/> goe the ſwifter, that thou maieſt the ſooner take reſt: be not made afraid for thy ſinnes, for if they be as redde as ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,<note place="margin">Eſai 1. &amp; 44.</note> they ſhalbe made as white as ſnow, as a cloude they ſhall be put away, and feare not to be accuſed of boldnes, where thou art prayſed for obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Goe and make haſte my ſoule vnto him, that came not to call the righteous, but ſinners, and<note place="margin">Matth. 8.</note> if thou art a ſinner, thy God is the God of ſinners. Wherefore then doeſt thou feare to goe, thou that art not called by a cruell iudge, but by the father of mercies, that thou mayeſt obtaine mercie: therefore goe now willing being called to mercie, that thou be not compelled hereafter to goe vnto iudgement. In thee, O Lorde, my noble Father doe I truſt, and will not be aſhamed
<pb facs="tcp:8753:28"/> to confeſſe vnto thee my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt</note> and blaſphemies, who was not aſhamed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them before men, and to barke againſt thee. Let the<note place="margin">Marke 2.</note> Phariſe murmure &amp; ſay, who can forgiue ſinnes but God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? for it is God that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto me, whoſe worde is liuely and effectuall, he that<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> calleth me is milde and pitiful, and is not wonted to containe his mercies in his wrath: And therefore vpon thy words will I aſſuredly come vnto thee, O my God, my truſt, and my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the land of the liuing. I wil come and fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and not feare thy Maieſtie, becauſe thou calleſt me, and that I offende not thine eyes when I ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vncleane in thy ſight. I will waſh away my filthineſſe with continuall teares, and
<pb facs="tcp:8753:29"/> mine eye lidde ſhall not reſt from weeping, but my bed ſhall be priuie vnto my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, wherein I pleaſe thee, though I diſpleaſe my ſelfe: and being by thee conuerted vnto thee, I repent me of thoſe things I haue committed, that I may praiſe thee with a cleane<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.</note> heart, ſaying, O Lord, who is like vnto thee? for then is thy<note place="margin">Eccl. 15. Pſal. 125.</note> praiſe bountifull in the mouth of a ſinner, and hee that hath ſowed in teares, ſhall reape in gladneſſe. <hi>Glory be to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt. As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="Psalm">
               <head>PSALM. VII.</head>
               <p>HAue mercie vpon me, O Lord, for I am in trouble, and vexed with vnſpeakeable miſeries: for floods of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doe vexe me, &amp; the waters<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8753:29"/> haue entred eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into my ſoule as a riuer that is ouerflowen, ſo my ſinnes which I haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therunto diſſembled, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to confeſſe, or amend, are growen ſo high that they haue paſſed ouer my head, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> bowed my minde and will, to the concupiſcence of ſenſuall deſires: yea, made me ſubiect to the ſlauerie of the deuil. Wo vnto me, for I am altogether mortally wounded, &amp; there is no health in me from the ſole of the foote, to the crowne of my head: for mine enemie hath ſupplanted me, and as a moſt cruell tyrant tormenting me, hath depriued me of all my ſenſes, leauing onely my vnderſtanding, that by ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the knowledge of my hurt and loſſe, he might alſo increaſe my ſorow. He ſhould litle hurt, if he had depriued
<pb facs="tcp:8753:30"/> me altogether of all vſe of my ſenſes, and had made me vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſenſeleſſe in all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but he hath depriued me thereof for doing that which is good, and hath violently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced me to euill: and hath ſo infected my minde, which is altogether bent to outward things, with a certaine aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of inward ſenſeleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſhe cannot feele her<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> inward hurtes: for when I ſhould haue heard, I was deafe, and turned mine eare from the trueth: but when it had beene fitte for mee to ſtoppe mine eares, from hearing vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things, and the toyes of many men, I was ſwift to heare, and a gentle hearer. Heauenly things I taſted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauerly, &amp; my ſoule lothed all ſpirituall meate, but I iudged earthly things ſweeter then
<pb facs="tcp:8753:30"/> the honie &amp; the honie combe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 100.</note> I was blinde, and an earthly man in beholding thoſe things that were Gods: but worldly things I looked vpon with a proude eye, and deſired them with an vnſatiable heart: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my ſenſes alone, but in my members alſo which God gaue to me for the ſeruice of my ſoule, did mine auncient enemie ſhut vp from me the way of ſaluation: and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch ambuſhes againſt me in this cruell ſiege, as I was neuer able to auoide them: but ſo often as I tried to flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I fell into his hands. For I did offend both by ſeeing, and refuſing to ſee, by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and by being deafe, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and holding my peace, ſtanding, and ſitting, ſleeping, and waking, walking, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: to conclude, I changed
<pb facs="tcp:8753:31"/> all the peculiar and common vſe of my ſenſes and members into a filthie abuſe, burning in my vncleane deſires, ſo that I haue tranſgreſſed all the lawes, both of God, man, and nature, and haue liued diligent in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing onely the law of ſinne. I would to God I onely had beene ſo, and nowe were not: but alas, becauſe I am yet the ſame that before I was, and nothing changed from that, I followed the worſt: for my ſicke will doeth yet beare rule, and my moſt foule &amp; ſtinking ſoule, that is filled euery where with horrible ſoares, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede only from it ſelfe, doeth ſtill perſeuere in the old euils. I am often angry with my ſelf, becauſe I am wearie to liue, when I am not weary to ſinne: I know my folly, and am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, &amp; being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:31"/> reproue my ſelf ſaying, O car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall louer, why doeſt thou ſo long wallowe in the mire of thy concupiſence? why art thou ſo carefully buſie for earthly things? and doeſt ſo earneſtly deſire thoſe goods which ſhall periſh? or with what reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calleſt thou goods, thoſe things thou gaineſt with ſo much labour, and the great hurt of thy ſoule, and being gained, poſſeſſeſt in feare, and being poſſeſſed, leeſeſt with griefe? O my ſoule, why doeſt thou forget thine owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eſtate, and nobilitie, and art not aſhamed to endure a miſerable and ſhamefull bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, vnder the corruption of thy corporall ſenſes? why art thou deceiued with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull promiſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world? &amp; markeſt not that the chiefe good thereof, is a vapour that
<pb facs="tcp:8753:32"/> appeareth but a little ſeaſon, and a vanitie of vanities? Bluſh, and be aſhamed, O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner, howe often haſt thou departed from thy Creatour, and turned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull creatures? and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againe to thy ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde with any ſight of thy minde, how cruelly in reſpect<note place="margin">S. Bernar.</note> of a miſerable hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting thy ſoule hath bowelled her ſelfe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt with an immoderate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, catching at a vile praye of flies, ſhee hath like the ſpider made nets for her ſelfe of her owne bowels. Againe and<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> againe I ſay, Bluſh at that wherein thou haſt had no fruite, and lament thy loſt time, that bluſhing, may bring<note place="margin">Prou. 23.</note> thee fruite: Yeelde thy heart vnto God, and thou ſhalt pay that thou oweſt. With theſe ſpeeches I rage againſt my
<pb facs="tcp:8753:32"/> ſelfe, when being inwardly admoniſhed, I enter into my ſelfe, and conſider with my heart what I haue loſt, and what I haue found: but I doe<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> not that good which I like, but the euill that I will, that I doe: for mine enemie holdeth my will, and doeth keepe me being faſhioned according to the former deſires of mine ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance captiue vnder the law<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> of ſinne: But thou, O Lorde God of vertues, the tower of my ſtrength, and the ruler of my life, doe not withdrawe thy helpe from me, looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my defence, and protect me<note place="margin">Pſal. 25</note> vnder the ſhadowe of thy wings, leaſt I fall in the ſight of mine aduerſaries, and mine enemie reioycing againſt me ſay, I haue preuailed againſt him: Breake the bands of my reproch, vnder which I haue
<pb facs="tcp:8753:33"/> beene made crooked, and loſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cordes of my ſinnes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I am ſtrongly bounde, O moſt mightie Lorde, and make knowen thy power vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine enemies, that I may offer vnto thee a ſacrifice of gladneſſe, ſaying: Who ſhall<note place="margin">Pſal. 105</note> ſpeake the power of the Lord, or who ſhall declare all his prayſes? that deliuered my ſoule from death, my feete from ſliding? who hath ſaued me from the lyons mouth, and my lowlineſſe from the hornes of Vnicornes. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.</note> I crie, but to thee, vpon whom all our fathers haue called, and haue beene ſaued? to thee, I ſay, who neuer deceiueſt them that hope in thee, ſet me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neere thee, and let any mans hand ſight againſt me: for I will feare no euill, becauſe thou art with me. All my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb facs="tcp:8753:33"/> are before thee, blot out and put away whatſoeuer is ſtrange from thee: renue, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and confirme whatſoeuer thou haſt giuen me, that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting away all carnall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable deſires, the ſinner may bee prayſed, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> of his heart, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to enioy thee the onely<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> true pleaſure, my requeſt may come before thy face, and I may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidently ſay vnto thee:<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> graunt vnto him, O my God, the deſire of my ſoule: for I knowe and am aſſured, that<note place="margin">Iob 6.</note> no man can deſire thee but by thy ſelfe, nor come vnto thee, vnleſſe thou draw him: Drawe me therefore, O Lorde, and graunt vnto me, that I may begin in a good deſire, that I may ende and perfite it in a good worke, before my olde cuſtome oppreſſe my newe
<pb facs="tcp:8753:34"/> deſire, &amp; my former will ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by age, conquer my newe will: leaſt when right things pleaſe me, I returne to my old wont. Clothe me with the precious garments of thy ſaluation and thy beautie, and put off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me the vile clothes of my widdowhead, wherein<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> being depriued of thee, I walke according to the ancient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the old man: &amp; doe not any more remember the ſhame of my widdowhead, that being newely clothed in<note place="margin">Eſai. 54.</note> thee, &amp; become a newe man, I may with a newe ſpirit ſerue thee in newnes of life, and in the ſweete ſmell of thine oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts running vnto thee, I may<note place="margin">Abac. 1.</note> reioyce in Ieſu my Sauiour. <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghost. As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Pſalmes.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:34"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A thankeſgiuing of a</hi> contrite Sinner, <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning pardon from</hi> God of his ſinnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Render vnto thee infinite thankes, O moſt gracious and mercifull God, for that remembring my ſo many ſinnes, I feare not for them, nor am aſhamed to confeſſe mine iniquities againſt thee, to thee: that I may confeſſe vnto thy Name, thy mercie towards me. For thou haſt had mercie vpon earth and aſhes, and it hath pleaſed thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in thy ſight, all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities, and to keepe me from many waters, leaſt the deapth ſhoulde ſwallowe me vp. I was going the right way
<pb facs="tcp:8753:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8753:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8753:36"/> vnto hell, carying all my ſinnes that I had comitted with me, vnleſſe thou, O Lord my God, and my guider, diddeſt bring me, that was going downe headlong, backe vnto thee, who art the way, the trueth, and the life: and diddeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten<note place="margin">Iohn 14.</note> my cloudie mind, with the brightneſſe of thy light, that ſeeing my ſelfe in the land of forgetfulnes, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of vnlikelineſſe, I might cal vnto thee out of the deepes of my ignorance, and knowe that thou art God my Sauiour and deliuerer, that haſt drawen me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my moſt wicked waies, and put goades vnto me, that I might therewith be pulled away. What ſhall I therefore render vnto thee, my beautie, my ſweeteneſſe, my part, God for euermore, for the maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous wayes that thou haſt vſed,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:36"/> to correct and direct my waies into the way of ſaluation? I was caried away into vanities, forgetting thee, O my God, and made my waies farre from thee, when thou moued with mercie ouer me, diddeſt call backe my filthie life, from the durt of earthly pleaſure, and diddeſt reſtraine my vntamed<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> minde, with the bit and bridle of calamities and labours, that I might come neere vnto thee.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> I wil therefore willingly glory in mine afflictions and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that thy grace may dwell in me, to whom I am a debter, for that thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen me ſo many euils, and haſt diſſolued my ſinnes like iſe. And for my ſorowes, as for thy giftes &amp; benefites (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by my ſoule hath beene ſaued) yeelding thankes vnto thee, I<note place="margin">Oſee 14. Pſal. 102.</note> will offer vp the calues of my
<pb facs="tcp:8753:37"/> lips, ſaying: Bleſſe the Lord, O<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> my ſoule, and doe not forget all his benefites, which is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto all thine iniquities, and healeth all thine infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who hath redeemed thy life from death, and crowneth thee in pitie and mercie, and filleth in good things thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Beholde howe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of thy mercies, wherein thou haſt lightened me, O my God, haue taken me, that I might imbrace thee, aboue all ſeducements that I followed: therefore I pray thee, my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the height of my humilitie, and reſt of my labour, doe not faint in helping me, that I alſo may not faint, in confeſſing vnto thee thy mercies. But graciouſly accept the ſacrifice of my confeſſions, from the hand of my mouth, and graunt vnto me the ſpirite of feare,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:37"/> that my ſoule conceauing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy promiſes, may henceforth be cheriſhed with heauenly things, and bring foorth the ſpirite of ſaluation. Protect me vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadow of thy hands,<note place="margin">Eſai 49. Prou. 5.</note> and cheriſh me in the boſome of thy mercies, leaſt they that paſſe in the way, treade vpon the vnfeathered fowle: But<note place="margin">S. Augu.</note> ſend thine angel, that may put him againe into the neſt, that he may liue vntill he may flie, and continually cleaue vnto thee, with daily praiers knocke vnto thee, poſſeſſe thee in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that thou mayeſt be vnto him all in all. As the young ſwallowes or doues, mourning<note place="margin">Eſai. 38.</note> doe call for meate vnto their mother: ſo I, mourning &amp; wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in this valley of teares, do crie vnto thee, my God, &amp; my helper in time of neede, that thou deliuer me from al temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb facs="tcp:8753:38"/> euen to the ende, and nouriſh me yet as a ſucking childe, that hauing receiued the ſtrength of thy vertue, as<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> long as I ſhall runne in the courſe of this worlde, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that which is behind, &amp; earneſtly bending my ſelfe to that which is before, with thy company &amp; protection, I may goe on to the appointed place, to the reward of the heauenly vocation, in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, who liueth &amp; raigneth with thee, in the vnitie of the holy ſpirit, God world without end. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>EPITAPHIVM</hi> D. ANTONII <hi>Luſitaniae Regis Sereniſſimi.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>PAreatibi vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rapuit, diadema Philippus,</l>
               <l>Et ſimul Oceaſus ac Orientis opes,</l>
               <l>Plus tibi reſtituit pietas tua, reddidit atque</l>
               <l>Quicquid habet tellus, ſidera quicquid habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="prosopopoeia">
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:39"/>
            <head>EIVSDEM REGIS <hi>LVSITAN.</hi> PROSOPOPEIA.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>PORTVG ALLORVM Regi mihi Gallia portus </hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na fuit, mihi Rex hic Deus, ille lupus.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Me patrio Regni ſolio fraudarat Iberus: </hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Electum HENRICVS Rex putate fouet.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Quaqueregit virtute pari Regina Britannos, </hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Lutore ſuſcepit me ELISABETH A ſue.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Grand euum tandem me Rex Coelſque ſolique, </hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>In ſedem miſtrans transtulit aetheream.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Page 1. line 15. haue, reade not haue.</p>
            <p>P. 5. l. 8. knowe, reade knewe.</p>
            <p>P. 8. l. 24. ſelfe, reade life.</p>
            <p>P. 12. l. 17. in ſinnes, reade in my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>P. 13. l. 1. a foole, reade as a foole.</p>
            <p>P. 13. l. 11. haling, reade hating. and l.</p>
            <p>14. wilfulnes, reade wilfulnes to ſinne.</p>
            <p>P. 13. l. 22. brought, reade bought.</p>
            <p>P. 19. l. 14. girfes, reade giftes. and l. 19.</p>
            <p>I fained, reade vnrecouerably I fained.</p>
            <p>P. 25. l. 9. reade nation, I am thy ſaluation.</p>
            <p>P. 41. l. 12. ſtrong, reade ſtrange.</p>
            <p>P. 52. l. 12. bountifull, reade beautifull.</p>
            <p>P. 56. l. 7. liued, reade beene.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8753:39"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
